<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Coronavirus on roryverse</title>
    <link>http://rorynolan.rbind.io/tags/coronavirus/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Coronavirus on roryverse</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2018</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="/tags/coronavirus/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Deaths per capita from COVID-19 are more informative than confirmed cases</title>
      <link>http://rorynolan.rbind.io/2020/01/01/covid19deathspercapita/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://rorynolan.rbind.io/2020/01/01/covid19deathspercapita/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The rate of testing for COVID-19 is variable everywhere. As such, using the number of confirmed cases over time is not a reliable method for tracking the spread of the disease.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;we-should-be-using-deaths-per-capita&#34; class=&#34;section level1&#34;&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;We should be using deaths per capita&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First of all, we should be using per capita statistics. For example, 100,000 cases in China vs 100,000 cases in Ireland would be very different things, because of what they imply for concentration of cases. Per capita (assuming a billion people in China and 5 million in Ireland), this would mean 1% of people in Ireland have the disease compared to 0.01% of people in China: 1 in 100 vs 1 in 10,000. Of course, just using per capita by country, you miss a lot too. A particularly high concentration of cases in Wuhan is not the same as a more even spread of cases throughout China. You can fix this by dividing by province or county (if you have that level of granularity in your data); I do this by state for the US. I’m going to use per million people instead of per capita, because it’s a bit easier to think about.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Second, reported deaths from the virus are more reliable than confirmed cases. That’s because the more ill you are, the more likely you are to get a test. The number of people &lt;em&gt;reported&lt;/em&gt; to have died of COVID-19 infection will be closer to the true number of people who died of COVID-19 than the number of people &lt;em&gt;reported&lt;/em&gt; to be infected will be to the true number of infected individuals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For timelining, I’ll use days since the tenth confirmed death from COVID-19.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;deaths-per-capita-will-lag-other-measures&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Deaths per capita will lag other measures&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don’t mean to say that deaths per capita is the only useful thing. It actually lags other measures (in particular the number of infected individuals) by a few days because the disease does not kill quickly. In particular, if a countries rate of testing is steady or increasing but the absolute number of people testing positive per day is decreasing, that’s a great sign and a sign that you’ll see sooner than a drop in deaths.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;data-source-preparation-and-limitations&#34; class=&#34;section level1&#34;&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Data source, preparation and limitations&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Johns Hopkins University Center for Systems Science and Engineering (JHU CSSE) has put together a great &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/CSSEGISandData/COVID-19&#34;&gt;COVID-19 data repository&lt;/a&gt;. Note that I’ve smoothed the data to make the plots more readable. This means that only sustained changes will appear on the plots (e.g. a one-day drop in deaths will be smoothed out). This is a good thing as it prevents us from reading too much into single data. Bear in mind that different countries have different measurement methods and capabilities, so they aren’t strictly comparable. However, provided that within a given country, the measurements are done in a consistent manner, one can still do reliable comparisons of the &lt;em&gt;shapes&lt;/em&gt; of the countries’ curves.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;world-data&#34; class=&#34;section level1&#34;&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;World data&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;all-countries&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;All countries&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m going to limit the data to countries that have reported at least 100 deaths. First up, I’ll just plot all of these countries. I’ll give a table of country codes at the end. Note that the data is not cumulative: each data point is deaths per million on that day. The lines are colored by how bad the situation is in that country right now: how many deaths there were there yesterday.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://rorynolan.rbind.io/post/2020-01-01-covid19deaths_files/figure-html/all-countries-1.png&#34; width=&#34;960&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;us-data&#34; class=&#34;section level1&#34;&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;US data&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m going to use the same limitations for the US state data: states with at least 100 deaths. For reference, I’m also going to include Spain and Italy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://rorynolan.rbind.io/post/2020-01-01-covid19deaths_files/figure-html/us-plot-1.png&#34; width=&#34;960&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;appendix&#34; class=&#34;section level1&#34;&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Appendix&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr class=&#34;header&#34;&gt;
&lt;th align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;iso3c&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;country&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;iso3c&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;country&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;iso3c&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;country&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr class=&#34;odd&#34;&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;AFG&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;Afghanistan&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;ECU&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;Ecuador&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;MEX&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;Mexico&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class=&#34;even&#34;&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;ARE&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;United Arab Emirates&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;EGY&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;Egypt&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;MYS&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;Malaysia&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class=&#34;odd&#34;&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;ARG&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;Argentina&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;ESP&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;Spain&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;NGA&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;Nigeria&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class=&#34;even&#34;&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;AUT&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;Austria&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;FIN&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;Finland&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;NLD&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;Netherlands&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class=&#34;odd&#34;&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;BEL&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;Belgium&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;FRA&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;France&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;NOR&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;Norway&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class=&#34;even&#34;&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;BGD&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;Bangladesh&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;GBR&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;United Kingdom&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;PAK&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;Pakistan&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class=&#34;odd&#34;&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;BIH&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;Bosnia and Herzegovina&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;GRC&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;Greece&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;PAN&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;Panama&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class=&#34;even&#34;&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;BLR&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;Belarus&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;HND&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;Honduras&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;PER&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;Peru&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class=&#34;odd&#34;&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;BOL&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;Bolivia&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;HUN&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;Hungary&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;PHL&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;Philippines&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class=&#34;even&#34;&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;BRA&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;Brazil&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;IDN&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;Indonesia&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;POL&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;Poland&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class=&#34;odd&#34;&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;CAN&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;Canada&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;IND&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;India&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;PRT&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;Portugal&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class=&#34;even&#34;&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;CHE&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;Switzerland&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;IRL&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;Ireland&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;ROU&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;Romania&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class=&#34;odd&#34;&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;CHL&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;Chile&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;IRN&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;Iran&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;RUS&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;Russia&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class=&#34;even&#34;&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;CHN&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;China&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;IRQ&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;Iraq&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;SAU&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;Saudi Arabia&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class=&#34;odd&#34;&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;CMR&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;Cameroon&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;ISR&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;Israel&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;SRB&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;Serbia&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class=&#34;even&#34;&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;COL&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;Colombia&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;ITA&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;Italy&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;SVN&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;Slovenia&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class=&#34;odd&#34;&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;CZE&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;Czechia&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;JPN&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;Japan&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;SWE&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;Sweden&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class=&#34;even&#34;&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;DEU&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;Germany&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;KOR&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;Korea, South&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;TUR&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;Turkey&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class=&#34;odd&#34;&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;DNK&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;Denmark&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;LUX&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;Luxembourg&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;UKR&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;Ukraine&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class=&#34;even&#34;&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;DOM&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;Dominican Republic&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;MAR&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;Morocco&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;ZAF&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;South Africa&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class=&#34;odd&#34;&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;DZA&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;Algeria&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;MDA&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;Moldova&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>I worked on the Bernie campaign. We lost. I feel bitter.</title>
      <link>http://rorynolan.rbind.io/2020/01/01/bernie1/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://rorynolan.rbind.io/2020/01/01/bernie1/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div id=&#34;disclaimer&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Disclaimer&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a report of how I found it working on the Bernie campaign, mixed with opinions of mine about what happened. I went into 2020 as a Warren and Sanders fan, and so remain. I don’t like the Democratic Party. I would rather them to the GOP, but I would rather an unpolished turd to the GOP. This piece is reflective of this point of view. I welcome comment from other points of view (though I rarely get that; friends and even family members are for the most part very unwilling to engage in political discussion here, for fear of I don’t know what).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;four-years-ago&#34; class=&#34;section level1&#34;&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Four years ago&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Brexit referendum of 2016 frightened me. I desperately wanted Britain to remain in the EU. I voted and hoped other people wouldn’t be &lt;em&gt;stupid&lt;/em&gt; and vote the other way. In other words, I did almost nothing other than feeling clever, followed by feeling disappointed. I had seen other people out campaigning for remain, but somehow I felt that that was a job for &lt;em&gt;those&lt;/em&gt; people. I still don’t understand why. Maybe I didn’t care as much as I said I did when I had a pint in my hand, or maybe I was just plain &lt;em&gt;stupid&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;section&#34; class=&#34;section level1&#34;&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;2019&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I met an American girl in England in 2015. I married her in 2018 and in 2019 I moved to California with her. As Christmas approached, the Democratic Party primary was taking shape. I was particularly excited about Elizabeth Warren and Bernie Sanders. Paul Krugman explained this infatuation well in a January 2020 interview with Ezra Klein, saying “Something went wrong in the US to lead us to where we are now; only Bernie Sanders and Elizabeth Warren have a theory of what that was.” This is perhaps unfair on people like Andrew Yang (I cannot understand why he was never taken seriously but Mayor Pete was), but it captures the general idea.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So yes, you could say I’m on the left. I want the government to provide healthcare without charges (call that &lt;em&gt;Medicare for all&lt;/em&gt; if you want to). I want taxes to be raised on people as lucky as myself (I’m an overpaid tech worker) or luckier to pay for things for people who don’t have enough. I want to stop fossil fuel exploration.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Towards the end of 2019, Elizabeth Warren was rising in the polls. She almost caught Joe Biden; it was an exciting time. Being a frontrunner coming from the left, she faced an enormous amount of scrutiny. The New York Times, Washington Post, MSNBC pummeled her on the unaffordability of her &lt;em&gt;Medicare for All&lt;/em&gt; plan, which was originally just an endorsement of Sanders’ plan. The pressure told. She wriggled around and came up with her own plan, slightly more &lt;em&gt;moderate&lt;/em&gt; than the original. Warren the flip flopper was kicked a few more times when she was down and that was the end of her. She had a notable moment left in her—roasting Mike Bloombberg alive on live TV—but she never had a shot again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile Bernie Sanders had a heart attack and in a quite incredible feat of loyalty from his supporters, managed to brush it off and carry on with his campaign. He seemed to avoid the intense criticism on medicare for all that Warren sustained. You’re only allowed to believe in that if you’re not going to win.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In fall (that’s autumn for you Europeans) of 2019, I had tried a few times to get involved in the Warren campaign, but they were slow in getting back to me; they didn’t really seem to be up and running in California. When I tried to get involved with the Bernie campaign, it was quickly evident that this was already a well-oiled machine in my locality.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;section-1&#34; class=&#34;section level1&#34;&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;2020&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m in, I’m working for Bernie (call me a bro if it makes you feel good). My day job at the time was contract work at Facebook, so I was villain by day, hero at night (at least in my own head). The work at Facebook was so fantastically undemanding that I had a lot of time and energy to devote to Bernie work. I never did Bernie stuff at work, but I could often leave early. The Oakland campaign office was on my block and I was in there more nights than not in the month before Super Tuesday (which includes the California primary).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I met lots of wonderful Bernie supporters on the campaign. Most people had one particular issue that they cared about. I think it’s interesting for a moment to dwell on who cared about what (of course I’ll have to generalise). There were a lot of teachers and nurses, who cared about schools and healthcare. They also cared about their own wages, as they should; their wages under-value their work. There were a hell of a lot of young people. They fear climate change and environmental destruction. I’ll put myself into that category. There were a lot of old people (ages 60 and above). They were very angry about American foreign policy. Iraq was the last straw for them. The Obama administration’s continued support for Saudi Arabia in their war with Yemen was last plus one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
